Watch this video and try to guess what's
happening.
[Music]
Did you guess what's happening? This is
Sia from Kazakhstan opening her IELTS
results. What were they? Well, she got
reading nine, listening nine, writing
eight, and speaking nine. So, overall
band nine. And as you can tell, well, as
you can almost tell, she is ecstatic.
It's hard to tell whether she's ecstatic
or sad, but yes, she is super super
happy to get such an amazing IELTS
score. She's probably in the like
0.001% of IELTS test takers. I've only
really ever met one other person that's
got overall bad nine. So, it's
absolutely incredible. Anyway, we met up
and we did an IELTS mock test and that's
what I'm going to show you today. So,
watch the mock test and learn from all
of the great vocabulary tactics and
techniques that Sia uses in this
speaking mock test. And stick around
until the end because Sia gives you some
great advice for how to improve your
English and IELTS skills. All right,
enjoy. Good morning. My name is Eli
Hows. Can you please tell me your full
name? Of course. My full name is Sai
Kidi. You can call me by my first name,
Sia. In this first part, I'd like to ask
you some questions about yourself. Let's
talk about what you do. Do you work or
are you a student? I'm a senior in high
school. So, I'm graduating this year.
What subjects are you studying? Well,
since I study in a public high school, I
don't really have a choice the subjects
that I get to study. So, I have to study
some compulsory subjects like calculus,
history, literature, and there are some
extracurricular activities like drama
classes and swimming that I can take.
However, since I am preparing for my
exams and for my college admission, um I
don't really have time to take up those
extracurricular activities. And what
would you like to do in the future?
That's a really interesting question.
I'm really into political science. So,
probably that's the sphere uh where I'll
pursue my bachelor's and hopefully
master's degree and maybe my career as
well. Let's move on. Let's talk about
cafes. Do you have a favorite cafe? Uh,
sure. It is a place right near my house.
It's a warm, cozy place. What makes it
special is the friendly atmosphere
there. Um, also I love the attention and
love with which the staff make each cup
of coffee. It makes the experience even
more enjoyable. Do you often go to cafes
by yourself? Yes, I find uh cafes to be
a perfect place to work and or unwind
with a book because the hum of
background conversations coupled with
some soft music, they give you the
feeling of concentration without the
feeling of isolation. What do you think
helps to make a cafe popular? Well, uh,
there are several factors that make a
certain cafe popular among people. The
first that immediately springs to my
mind is a word of mouth recommendations.
I mean, if a cafe has good food there,
good service um, and etc. People would
be more likely to visit it again
probably with their friends. So, it
would help to grow it a loyal clientele.
Um also we have to consider that since
we live in a digital era uh era it is
important to pay attention to media
presence. So if cafes make their uh
Instagram, Tik Tok or even maybe YouTube
pages more attractive to visitors, it
can play a significant role in their
popularity. Why do some people prefer
cafes that are part of larger chains
rather than small local independent
cafes? Wow, that's a really interesting
question. probably because international
cafe chains, they are um they seem more
reliable to people because they already
know what to expect and usually they
offer certain conveniences like huge
parking spaces or reliable Wi-Fi to
their uh customers. Let's move on. Let's
talk about perfume. Do you like to use
perfume? I love perfume. It's honestly a
part of my outfit. If I do not have
perfume on, I feel as if there's a part
of my outfit that's missing. So,
honestly, I have a very big collection
of perfumes that I use. And in fact, all
of my family members are obsessed with
um like smell and with perfume. So, I
think it's something that runs in my
runs in my blood. And how often do you
wear perfume? Every single day. I wear
different perfume. every single day. By
the way, um that depends on my mood and
what outfit I'm wearing for the day.
Have you ever given perfume as a gift?
Well, um I did not really think that it
is a good sign to give perfume, at least
in our culture in Kazakhstan. Uh but to
my international friends that came
visiting from Italy, there was a certain
perfume uh that I bought from the UAE
and it had a very specific smell that I
knew that my Italian friends would
enjoy. So I that was the only occasion
when I gave perfume as a present. Um
although I've been to many different
places with beautiful scenery, there is
a place that has a special um place in
my heart and it is the Swiss Alps. I
think the Swiss Alps are famous
worldwide for how beautiful the
mountains are, especially in the winter.
and I had the opportunity to visit the
Swiss Alps last December with my family
as we were staying there for a family
holiday. It was a very interesting
destination and a very interesting
choice that I've made because I got to
choose where our family was heading. And
the country that immediately sprung to
my mind was Switzerland because I know
that Switzerland is known for its
gorgeous nature. And since we visited uh
Switzerland in December, we decided to
go to the Alps and stay in a very um
small village that is not densely
populated. And that gave us a chance to
enjoy the beauty of the mountains fully
because we were able to see huskys
running all over the place. And we were
able to go snowboarding and hiking which
was very enjoyable because of the fresh
air and the freshness that um the Swiss
Alps offer. Since we've been there in
December, we got to the airport right
after fresh snowfall and that made the
experience even more surreal. We also
got to visit a few virgin forests. The
experience is indescribable because the
nature there is was unexpectedly
beautiful. I've never thought that I
would be lost for words when I saw this
scenery. It was a totally picture skew
scenery. Also, our hotel room had a
beautiful view of a lake that had a
glass-like coverage on it, and it felt
as if we can go ice skating there, but
unfortunately. Thank you. Would you like
to return to the Swiss Alps? Um, sure.
If I ever get an opportunity again, I'd
love to go there. Okay. So, we've been
talking about a place that you've been
to that has phenomenal views, and I'd
like to discuss with you one or two more
general questions related to this. Let's
consider first of all the beauty
industry. Now, some people say that
beauty products are a waste of money.
What do you think? Well, um on the one
hand, some products really are overhyped
and they do not uh they're not worth the
hype that they're getting from the
audience. But on the other hand, there
are some products that serve a genuine
purpose. for example, they can improve
your skin, make your skin brighter, and
reduce your acne, for example. So yeah,
while some products are overly estimated
and they are not worth the attention
that they're getting, there are many
other products that are in fact helpful
and useful not only in terms of
improving your skin uh improving your
skin and the way that you look like your
natural appearances, but also in
boosting your self-confidence.
How do you think the beauty industry
advertised their products so
successfully? Well, I believe that the
way that the marketing um sphere is
built and the way that they market their
products is very interesting because the
beauty industry itself downplays on the
humans's most important need and that's
the need to be accepted by society. So
they make up their own insecurities.
They bring up the insecurities in women
and they make their products sort of the
answer towards the insecurity. And it's
really interesting how they do it
because once uh women feel insecure
about something, they search for a
project that solves the problem and it
turns out that the solution is their
product. Yes, that's very true. So, do
you think that possibly beauty companies
should not be allowed to advertise to
children? probably yes because
children's minds are not fully formed
yet and their cognitive processes are
still developing. Therefore, they might
be way more vulnerable than any other
group let's say of people towards these
aggressive marketing actions. So I do
believe that children especially young
girls should not be a target for
marketing campaigns. Let's move on.
Let's talk about beauty and culture. Why
is it that so many people equate beauty
with youth? Well, there are cert there
are several reasons for this. The first
one is the way that youth is being
promoted in the media. Like we consider
people who do not have wrinkles, who
have this who have these youthful
features, beautiful. And that's partly
because of the way that we are
programmed biologically. like
evolutionary people who are young are
considered to be more viable and since
they are they since they have more
ability to um prolong um their life and
to live a longer life they are
considered to be more attractive towards
uh for example other sexes or towards
like their partners and etc. So I
believe that there is a twist of
evolution but also um media also adds
certain sprinkles of the way that we see
how youth is equal to beauty. Now do you
think that people that are beautiful or
people's level of beauty can affect
their success in life? Many in many ways
we find that physically attractive
people they are more successful in
career in business in for example even
deals because we are people we're not
logical we are biological creatures and
that's why physical attractiveness makes
one look more trustworthy as a business
partner or as for example if you're an
investor you are more likely to invest
in a physically attractive or in other
words a conventionally beautiful
person's business or project even if
their business model is weaker in many
respects than the other person who's not
maybe as attractive. Sounds like a sad
thing to me. What about you? It is a
negative development because truly there
are geniuses who may not objectively
look physically attractive but their
ideas are worth millions and billions of
dollars but because of the way that we
are wired they may not have the same
opportunity or they might have to work a
lot harder than their more attractive
counterparts. So we may state that the
society may be losing a lot of geniuses
because of this conception. Thank you
very much. That is the end of the
speaking test. What an amazing speaking
test. That was incredible. Now Sia, I
know you've already scored band nine.
You've got the top score in IELTS
speaking. And I know that you actually
got overall band N, which is incredible.
I think you're in the
0.001% of IELTS test takers that have
been able to achieve such a high score.
And the amazing thing that I experienced
was your level just went from strength
to strength. Part one was good, part two
was even better, and part three was
phenomenal. You were dealing with some
really difficult concepts, and you were
explaining your ideas so articulately
and so well. How do you do that? Give us
some tips. What can people do to to get
to your level of English? Uh, thank you
so much, Eli, for your feedback. Uh well
in terms of improving speaking I'd say
that if a person is at a beginners or
like at the starters level one thing
that they can do is shadowing a
technique that I have used throughout my
English learning journey. It is a very
effective technique since it helps you
improve not only your speaking but also
your listening at the same time. uh
particularly shadowing helps to improve
fluency and coherence marking criteria
that are very important in IELTS as far
as I'm concerned. Uh the other technique
that I would use is reading a lot and
not just reading reading out loud. It's
very important because when you hear
yourself read, you tend to remember the
grammatical structures even if they are
way more complex than the grammatical
structures that you are used to using.
In this way, you are sort of putting
your brain into an environment when they
are learning the English language in a
natural way. In other words, you're
learning the English language as if
you're as if you're learning or as if
you were learning your mother tongue
because primarily when we were learning
our mother tongue, our first language,
nobody gave us a textbook, nobody gave
us, you know, grammatical rules. We had
to learn it through the immersion
method. The same with English. And it's
very important to understand that if the
first technique, the shadowing technique
can really um enhance your
pronunciation, your accent for example,
right? You can acquire a British,
American, whatever accent you want by
repeating what native speakers say. The
second technique is really important to
develop um eloquence and your ability to
transmit and convey your thoughts in a
very structured and cohesive manner
because we all know that in any given
language even if that is a language that
you've been speaking for years like from
the day that you were born in order to
increase the level of your um of how
structured you speak of your uh
coherence in even your native language,
you need to read a lot because reading
helps you get that me mental fog away
from your brain when you're speaking and
helps you think in more structured bits.
I really noticed about your answers your
way of thinking is very organized. So
you said well there are several factors
first of all and then you would
introduce the first idea and then you
would develop it probably with an
example and then you would say second of
all and it's almost like if I were to
see a transcript of your answers I'd be
very impressed because I could read it
and immediately pinpoint what you were
talking about at every second of your of
your conversation. So is that something
you do deliberately or is that something
that's naturally occurred as a result of
your shadowing and reading out loud
techniques? Well, naturally I don't
think that people do speak I don't think
that people speak in um organized and
structured in a structured manner
because we are very chaotic whenever we
speak like freely. But that is a
technique that I got to acquire when I
was preparing for the ISELS exam because
I figured that the examiner like a lot
of people do not understand that
examiners have a very hard time
assessing your level of English because
they have only 11 to 14 minutes and in
that very short amount of time they have
to figure out what your level is and
give you the most objective score. And I
figure that it's my job to help the
examiner assess my level as objectively
as possible. And in order to do that, I
figured that I need to use contrasting
language in order to show not only one
side but also the other side of the
issue. And that would help to show my
lexical resource as well as my ability
to use different cohesive devices
effectively to the examiner. Great. So,
how did you feel when you when you
opened your test report card and you saw
that you got overall ban nine? It was a
surreal moment because I've um you know
like I've been attempting to get the
score for six years and I've been
studying deliberately to get the score
and I took the test overall about 20
times if I'm not mistaken. I took my
first ISS at the age of 11 and got a 6.5
overall and 8.5 in section of speaking.
And for me back then I had the highest
possible level because for me at the age
of 11 English was the language that I
felt most comfortable conveying my
thoughts in. And that was like a big
disappointment because I did not even
get a seven like a C1. And then I took
the exam twice at the age of uh 15 and
got an overall of an eight and then I
scored 8.5 at the age of 16. However, I
knew that I could score higher. I had
this you know like feeling that what did
not give me um peace. I felt that I
could do much better. I can get this
nine. And you know like in every ESL or
EFL learners um journey there is this
you know trophy of getting a band nine
and it's like oh my god I want to get
this band nine. And I had this I had
this feeling I had this ambition of
getting a band nine at starting from my
first ever test like at the age of 11.
you could see interviews and I'd say I
want and I will get a band nine. And it
turns out that six years later, after
studying hard, after working
deliberately, I finally scored this uh
band, this perfect band nine. And when I
opened it up, I actually did not expect
to get a band nine because Eli, I've
been getting 8.5s like straight in a
row. I would get 8.5, 8.5. So I thought
that I would get an 8.5. Um, and then
when I saw this, you know, like number
nine, it felt as if I was hallucinating
and as if, you know, like I did not see
the number correctly. There's actually a
video of me reacting to my score and
it's it just went viral on the internet.
Um, I I called my mom and I said, I got
a nine finally. And it's a call that
I've been meaning and I've been wanting
to have like this conversation with my
mom for such a long time because can you
imagine 20 times over and over calling
your mom and saying, "Mom, I didn't do
this this time. I couldn't get B nine."
And it's 20 times like a failure. 20
times it's as if 20 times somebody pours
ice cold water onto you or somebody
gives you like the hardest slap of your
life. and finally getting to call my mom
and say, "Mom, I did this. Mom, thank
you so much for believing in me and
thank you so much for not giving up on
me because my mom was the person that
was all along the way." And she would
always say, "You can do this. I believe
in you. Just study harder. You can get
this sa and she was a person who was who
believed in me at times when I even did
not believe in myself or I did not have
the faith that I could do this anymore."
And that call was very special to me. So
she was the first person that that knew
about this band nine and then my whole
team knew and then as it appears um the
whole you know like the country
Kazakhstan knew and all of all everybody
was very proud and I was very proud of
myself and the work that I put to get
this band 9 because I don't think that
people understand how different like
bands 8.5 and bands nine are because it
seems as if it's only like um an 05
score difference, but it's actually not.
It's like getting a an 8.5, yes, that's
an amazing result. It's a C2 level, the
highest level possible in the English
language, but getting a nine means that
you're not only fluent like fluent in
the English language, but you're also
fluent in the exam of
ISAM works. And it just getting this
sort of let's say trophy or achieving
this score felt really surreal uh to me
at the moment. Wow. And I know that you
know now you pass on your tips, your
advice, your strategies on to other
people. So if people want to get in
contact with you, if they want to follow
your journey, what's the best way for
them to do that? Well, I have a very
active Instagram and Tik Tok page. They
can just type in sia like my first and
my last name and they'll see my
Instagram. They'll see my Tik Tok page.
And I'm planning to launch a YouTube
channel as well because I find that
formats like these 30 seconds reals
formats or very short video formats,
they may not be the most effective
medium to share my knowledge and share
my experience. So in the future, I'm
planning to launch YouTube channel, but
right now they can find me on Instagram
and on Tik Tok. That's great to hear.
Thank you so much for coming on and for
doing what was genuinely one of the most
impressive speaking tests I've ever
done. Thank you so much, Eli, for your
um for having me here. Thank you.